Guide to the Glenway Wescott and Monroe Wheeler Collection of Katherine Anne Porter
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Glenway Wescott and Monroe Wheeler collection of Katherine Anne Porter
1943-1983
YCAL MSS 153
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.13
(3 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, manuscript items, notes, and ephemera related to Porter which were found among the Wescott and Wheeler papers.
Porter, Katherine Anne, 1890-1980
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Received with the Glenway Wescott Papers and the Monroe Wheeler Papers, purchase from Monroe Wheeler, 1988, with later purchase and gift from Anatole Pohorilenko, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Additional Katherine Anne Porter material can be found in the Glenway Wescott Papers [YCAL MSS 134] and the Monroe Wheeler Papers [YCAL MSS 136]. The materials included in this collection represent items that were already segregated when received with the original papers.
KATHERINE ANNE PORTER, 1890-1980
Katherine Anne Porter, short story writer and novelist, known for Ship of Fools, was a long-time friend of Glenway Wescott and Monroe Wheeler.
Scope and Contents
The Glenway Wescott and Monroe Wheeler Collection of Katherine Anne Porter contains correspondence, manuscript items, notes, and ephemera related to Porter which were received with the Wescott and Wheeler papers. The material covers the dates 1943-83.
The collection is housed in 3 boxes and is organized into three series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings; and III. Other Material.
Series I, Correspondence, contains copies of letters from and about Porter, as well as early letters about the Katherine Anne Porter Foundation.
Series II, Writings, contains drafts (many inscribed to George Platt Lynes) and printed copies of works by Porter, along with a galley proof of Ship of Fools.
Series III, Other Material, consists of various items documenting Porter's life, including articles and clippings, and notes by Monroe Wheeler on Porter, among other items.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Porter, Katherine Anne, 1890-1980; Wescott, Glenway, 1901-1987; Wheeler, Monroe, 1899-1988
- Correspondence, 1951-1977; Series I; 0.21; (.5 box)
  - Library of Congress to KAP [copy], 1962 Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - KAP to Barrett Prettyman [copy], 1977 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - KAP to and from William R. Ross, University of Colorado [copies], 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Seeger, Pete, to Monroe Wheeler [copy], 1965 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Scope and Contents
    [re: KAP's French Song-Book]
  - University of Virginia Library to Lloyd Wescott [copy], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    [re: KAP manuscripts]
  - Correspondence re: Katherine Anne Porter Foundation, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Writings, 1934-1963; Series II; 0.21; (.5 box)
  - "The Calm, Pure Art of Willa Cather", review of Willa Cather on Writing, printed version, New York Times Book Review, 1949 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The Dark Forest", outline of a psychological love story, draft, typescript, mimeograph, 1947 Mar 6 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "I am no more what I once was", translation of song by Clément Marot, drafts, holograph and typescript (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Little Requiem", draft, typescript, 1946 Sep 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Love and Hate", printed version, Mademoiselle, 1948 Oct (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - [Notes from Davos], typescript carbon, 1934 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - [Notes], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Now No Spring", draft, typescript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Pale Horse, Pale Rider", stage version, program, 1963 Nov (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Pierre-Joseph Redouté", printed version, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ship of Fools, galley proof, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "This Strange Old World", review of The Secret Game by Francois Boyer and The House of Breath by William Goyen, printed version, New York Times Book Review, 1950 Aug 20 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Virginia Woolf's Essays, A Great Art, A Sober Craft", review of The Captain's Death Bed, printed version, New York Times Book Review, 1950 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "The Wooden Umbrella, notes on a self-portrait", draft, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Other Material, 1950-1983; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Articles on KAP, 1962-80 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Book catalog prices, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Cardboard enclosure signed by KAP, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper clippings on KAP, 1962-83 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Envelopes, annotated, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Invitations to events for KAP, 1962-73 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Memorial service invitations and programs, including one annotated by Anatole Pohorilenko, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Notes by Monroe Wheeler on KAP, ca. 1950-70s (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Oversize, 1962; 1.5; (1 box)
  - Newspaper clipping on KAP (in Series III), 1962 (Box 3, Folder 29)